the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license your support
will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational resources
for free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT opencourseware at ocw.mit.edu
okay so today we're going to continue
talking about multi-hop networks and in
particular I'm going to talk about a
fairly fundamental problem in multi
health networks called network routing
and that's the topic for today and for
threw through most of half of next week
and today this week we'll talk about
network routing in networks where there
are no failures so you know in real
networks of course things fail packets
get dropped nodes may fail switches may
fail links may fail we'll just worry
about the case when there are no
failures for this week next week we'll
add some more complexity and talk about
how we deal with failures so the
abstract problem is pretty simple you
have a set of nodes in the network and
there's some network topology
and every source in the network you know
you have sources and you have
destinations loads in the network and
they wish to send packets to each other
and we're going to decompose this
problem these endpoints which actually
want you to want to communicate with
each other as we've already talked about
do so by sending packets via switches
and the problem we're going to worry
about is what happens inside the network
in these switches the switches solved
the following problem if things work
correctly and if things work well when a
switch receives a packet with the
destination address specifying that that
packet has to be sent to a particular
named destination in the network the
switch figures are how to ship that
packet it figures out whether to send it
along I need a better topology here it's
sugarstar this switch for example
figures out whether a package should go
along that link or this link or this
link or this link or that link given any
packet that receives and every switch in
the network performs this task
now when a switch gets a packet and the
packet has the destination address in it
what the switch does is some sort of a
lookup it looks up that destination in
some sort of a table and that table
maintains information about which of the
links to use in sending that packet
toward the destination and this step is
called forwarding
packets are forwarded by switches
technically packets aren't routed
everybody says packet routing and I say
too but it's important to realize
packets aren't drought at packets are
forwarded the fumbling process is pretty
straightforward at slow speeds you get a
packet you take the destination you look
up that packet in a table and that table
tells you what you do with the packet
which link to use routing is the problem
that the switch is solved of
constructing these tables so forwarding
is simply look up in a table and the
table is called the routing table
sometimes it's also called the
forwarding table and there's a technical
difference between them that's not that
important for us so forwarding is the
process of looking up the destination in
the routing table routing is the
distributed process the algorithm that's
used or the protocol that's used to
build up these routing tables so it's
the construction process how to
construct these routing tables at each
switch in the network
that's done in the background that's
usually done in software switches that
high-speeds involve a fair amount of
hardware routing itself is usually done
in software and so a typical switch you
know has a lot of different processing
elements in it a lot of those processing
elements are high speed hardware that
deals with the process of forwarding and
then you have software sitting on the
side where all of the complexity is and
all that complexity deals with all sorts
of complicated rules that you have to
come up with in order to decide how to
construct these routing tables and we're
going to talk about the world's simplest
networks today where and you'll find
that even that's reasonably
sophisticated and complicated so just
for concreteness an example of a picture
of a topology is like this and for
reasons that will become apparent as we
talk this through will model the network
as a set of nodes and a set of links and
so far there's nothing new about this
but will model links as having the cost
and this cost might reflect for example
the delay or latency to send a packet
along that link the cost might reflect
the real dollar cost of shipping data
along links internet service providers
might charge different amounts of money
for different types of data for example
well the cost might just reflect your
own internal preferences as to which
links you might prefer based on whatever
concerns maybe some links are slow and
some links are fast maybe they're higher
speed link slower speed links that cost
more or less etc so these costs are
abstract numbers and we'll just assume
that we're interested in finding minimum
cost paths between senders and receivers
so every switch solves the problem of
finding the minimum cost path to a
destination where the cost along a path
is simply the sum of the costs along the
links on that path this is just standard
shortest path routing will use shortest
paths even though we don't mean
literally the shortest number of hops
but the minimum cost path and where that
distinction is important between the
number of hops and the cost etc we'll
five so if there aren't cable looks
something like this in fact it looks
like this
there's destination every switch has
this so this is an example of a round
table at load B node B maintains all the
destinations in the network and we're
dealing with small networks so far in
our class so we'll just assume that
every node in the network has a unique
name or a unique address and that the
destination that the routing tables
contain an entry for every destination
in the network so the arm table has
three columns it's a database with three
columns and every switch in the network
or a node I'm going to use the word node
and switch interchangeably every switch
or node in the network has one of these
if the network is working correctly so
if there aren't protocol that what does
this job every node comes up with its
own version of this table there's a
destination there's the link you need to
use that is the next hop if you get a
packet to this destination what link
would you use and a cost so in this
table if node B or switch B received a
packet destined for destination a it
would use link l1 each link is named
locally so B would have its own l0 l2
and l1 you know your own computer has a
bunch of links if you do I don't know
how what the command is in Windows but
in all other sensible platforms if you
do I have conveyed you can you can get I
think it's called IP config under
windows but you can actually see a list
of links so switches have many many many
links and so you'll find for example for
destination a you use link l1 the cost
is 18 in fact you'll see here that when
when B receives a packet for a it
doesn't use the direct link because the
direct link has a cost of 19 whereas
going through l1 this link has the cost
of 11 and if it believes if B believes
that this the path toward a along this
link has a cost of elemental 7 is 18
that's what it thinks and therefore it
would use that link
okay it's very simple now routing is the
process by which these different nodes
talk to each other and build up these
tables when I say a route to a
destination I mean this I mean the route
to a destination at a switch or at a
node is the link that that destination
would use to send packets to the
destination this is important
technically for us because otherwise we
will get all tangled up getting confused
between routes and paths okay for the
purposes of our discussion a route is
the next hop link is the link that
you're going to use to get to the
destination the path is a sequence of
links so I don't want people telling me
that the route from B to E is whatever
ever it is BCE I'd like people to tell
me that the route act destiny node B to
destination e is l1 or if you wish to be
clear you can say it's link l1 which
takes it to the next hop see the path
from B to E might be BCE okay
all right so that's what the routing
table structure looks like and we're
interested in minimum cost our paths to
go from places to places so you know
normally traditionally we sit around and
try to now dive into protocols but I
think here what we're going to do is
since our notes are also nice and
written up I actually don't have to tell
you everything that's there so what
we're actually going to do is something
we call the routing game which is an
experiment in social networking like
what it means is that each of you or
some of you will act as nodes and start
computing routes to different
destinations okay so that's what this
game is going to be so what I have in my
hand is 40 slips of paper and I hope
there are 40 people here 40 slips of
paper and each of these paper slips of
paper has some information that looks
like this it says you are node X and
you're connected to nodes Y Z W etc okay
and there's a set of rules that I will
go through in a minute first of all
these were all in perfect order so I
need to shuffle them a few times
carefully without losing them
I think persi diaconis is famous
probabilistic said that you got to do
the seven times okay so what I'm going
to do is I'm gonna pass this around
there's no bag here the bag is
cumbersome so what I'd like you to do
actually I'll put it in the envelope and
pass it around just kind of close your
eyes or something don't look at the
number and just pick one up and don't
look at it until I tell you okay so we
start here and just pass it around I'd
like you know 40 different people to
have them you don't you don't have to
feel compelled to take it but just pass
it around and try to do it quickly
because I'd like that to happen faster
than the time it's going to take for us
to compute these routes so why don't you
just pick one sheet of paper up and just
pass it around please
okay so though you know I picked seven
minutes sometimes works a little faster
than seven the best that the class is
down is about five minutes and sometimes
last term they did it very quickly but
they got it wrong so
I don't think that counts but I've been
told that they've tried this experiment
Berkeley has taken usually more than
seven minutes and I figure MIT students
are smarter so let's see if you can do
it faster than seven minutes now your
job is to find a path from a source node
to a destination or as quickly as
possible okay and I mean as a bonus if
you actually find the path with the
minimum number of hops that's even
better but we'll take any pack now
there's some rules here
now there are some rules here so you may
not actually kind of get up and run
around and try to you know do things
that a normal network switch wouldn't do
so you're allowed to stay in one place
and what you're actually allowed to do
is you're not allowed to pass your sheet
of paper to other people because you
know you have information about yourself
and that piece tells you who your
neigh​bors are the numbers of your
neigh​bors so you can't actually kind of
copy the Ascend your piece of paper to
other nodes that's not allowed and don't
don't let people copy what's on your
sheet of paper now here's some things
you can do you can read them ask your
friends for advice you can shout to
other participants we're allowing you to
you know yell and scream but do so in a
way that's somewhat civilized and you
know if you can wish that you didn't
pick up a slip or pick up a slip or
whatever but you know try to act
generally I mean this class is recorded
so you know what you say might be heard
now if you get to sleep a slip there's
some ground rules you can't cheat like
you know we're not dealing with security
here's where a node that's 17 and
connected to 27 and 29 tells people that
it's 14 I mean you don't want that it's
hard enough to do when you tell the
truth so don't cheat this you know
there's probably a variant of this we
can come up with where some fraction of
the nodes they're adversarial and then
you can see if this stuff even works but
right now don't cheat if you've got a
slip you kind of have to really try to
participate in whatever protocol you
come up with and this experiment has no
human subjects approval
okay so it does um who has the envelope
is it empty oh my goodness at seven
minutes already
let's okay well when the envelope gets
empty we can start this thing so we
should try to move it along
is everyone clear on the rules what
you're trying to do is to find a path
between a node that the source node
which was numbered one and the
destination node enough that was number
forty the source and the destination
know who they each are and then we'll
just gonna wait this is the easiest
lecture to prepare for because I just
have to keep quiet
for a few minutes okay and if things all
work out or things don't work whatever
it is I'm assuming that you'll come up
with some variant of the reasonable
routing protocol and odds are it will be
a variant of one of the ones we're going
to study you know the general hero's
suggest if something was a reasonable
idea which is you go and you know you
you do one you tell you you know you
pick one neigh​bor and you go through but
you get stuck in a loop and then the
idea is you come back to where you start
and then you go through the next and
that principle could work but you gotta
remember a lot of stuff and tends to
make mistakes in fact you know this was
an easy Network where every node had one
two or three neigh​bors I mean as a few
with more but most of them had a small
number of neigh​bors what you guys were
going after was a sort of better plan
which is everybody yells out the
neigh​bors and the day as yell out their
neigh​bors and their neigh​bors and so
forth and that particular protocol has a
nice name to it it's called link state
routing where you broadcast and flood
your own neigh​bor information okay
that's the second of the two protocols
we're going to study what you were
trying to go after was a link state
routing
now the first protocol we're gonna study
has a different name to it it's called
distance vector re
and these are the two routing protocols
we're going to study almost all routing
protocols and practice are variants of
either a vector protocol or one of these
link-state protocols there's lots of
variants but these cover and there's
hundreds of routing protocols but these
cover the main concepts so let me tell
you how this is our distance vector
protocol or how the vector protocols
works they're a little different from
the kind of approach you were going
after in solving this problem had you
gone after an approach where you started
at the destination at 40 and 40 simply
said I'm 40 and then the neigh​bors next
to 40 then said I'm connected to 40 to
get to 40 come through me and the cost
is let's say whatever the cost of their
link to 40 is right then now initially
nodes only knew about themselves but now
you have a destination and you have a
set of nodes connected to the
destination let's call these nodes let's
just say n1 n2 and n3
initially the only thing that D says is
I'm D and it says back to its neigh​bors
along these links the same has a name to
it it's in it's an advertisement now
when anyone hears about destination D it
can do the same thing to its neigh​bors
so let's say these are n4 and n5 here
what n1 can do is to say that to get to
D let's imagine that this cost here is 6
so D says I'm D and the cost to get to
me is 0 because I'm D n1 says here's
that and it says I'm n1 that's true but
to get to D come through me and the cost
is 6 so it now puts out advertisements
along these links but it says D : 6 6 6
where 6 is the cost of that link
and now let's imagine that you know
these other links have cost so let's say
this link has a cost of eight this link
has a cost of two let's say this link
has a cost of 9 so the link cost is
eight the link cost is nine and the link
cost is two and let's say for a minute
here that this cost of this link is
there now n1 advertises to everybody
saying to get 2d the cost is six to get
2d the cost to six and they get to get
2d the cost of six each of those guys
when they get this information now know
that they can get a route to destination
D because now and for now is that if it
used this link to get 2d the cost would
be six plus the cost of that link so
it's 14 so it would have a routing table
entry that says D is a cost 14 and of
course the routing table entry would
have an entry saying this is the link
that it should use similarly n5 here
would take destination D and say that
the cost to destination D is 9 plus the
advertisement which was 6 and so it
would say D is 15 and n 2 which
previously had her out today which was
this link that cost 10 would look at
this new advertisement coming in here
saying that the cost on this from n1 is
6 add that cost to the cost of the link
which is 2 and have now a different way
to get to D whose cost is 8 and compared
that cost against the cost a previously
held to the destination D and because
we're interested in minimum cost routing
8 smaller than 10 so n 2 would
previously which had previously had a
cost to destination D of 10 would throw
that route out
replace it with a route the destination
D going along this link with the cost of
now eight which is smaller than ten and
this process just continues through as
it goes along so you might end up in a
situation quite easily as we just went
through here well let's say n 3 will
connected to n 5 if this link had a cost
of 1 in this link at a cost of 4 what
would eventually happen is that n 5
which ended up with the cost of 15 to go
like that would when it here's an
advertisement from this node replace
that route with a cost of 4 and use this
link as its route to get to get the
destination D and this process just
continues until everybody has initially
some route to D and then if the process
continues a little bit longer everybody
will have a minimum cost route to D this
step where nodes evaluate an
advertisement that they hear about a
destination against their current route
and the current cost to the destination
and replace it if they end up finding a
route with smaller cost or an
advertisement with smaller cost when you
the cost you have to compare is the cost
of the advertisement plus the cost of
the link along which that advertisement
came and you compare that cost against
the cost of the route you already hold
if it's smaller you replace it that
algorithm is called the bellman-ford
algorithm
and you might have seen centralized
implementations of shortest path routing
using this algorithm and if you have it
actually turns out it's a little less
efficient than other algorithm another
one we'll study called Dijkstra's if
you're doing it centralized but it's
very very elegant elegant for
distributed computation because the
routes to different destinations are
being computed in a completely
distributed way these nodes far away
here have no idea what the network
topology looks like they couldn't even
reconstruct the network topology the
best they could do is to find their own
way to get you know their link to use
the only information they have is what
they hear from their neigh​bors but yet
they're able to find an answer because
all they have to do is to listen to all
their neigh​bors and among the set of
neigh​bors pick that neigh​bor whose
advertise cost plus the cost of the link
to that neigh​bor is minimum across all
of the neigh​bors so the computation
that's being done is a very simple
computation very elegant computation
which is the main over all of the
neigh​bors of the link cost lij plus the
advertised cost from j where the minimum
has gone over all are all j where j is
the set of neigh​bors so you minimize
over the set of the neigh​bors each node
I does this you minimize over the set of
neigh​bors J of I the link cost from I to
J plus the advertised past to
destination D of J and take the minimum
cost that's the minimum cost and then
you take the link corresponding to that
neigh​bor and that's the route that you
use
now this algorithm gets more complicated
and tricky to argue that it's correct
when there are failures but today there
are no failures there's some other
wrinkles in the algorithm which is I
mentioned that you know what are the
conditions under which a link node
changes its route to a destination so I
went through one rule I I mentioned a
rule that said if the current copy if
the current route to the destination
does not exist in which case the cost is
assumed to be infinity or if the current
cost to the destination is smaller than
the cost of the advertisement plus the
cost of the link along which the
advertisement came then you replace the
route to the destination but there's
actually one other condition under which
you should replace the route to the
destination
if it's equal well technically you don't
have to replace it you still have a good
pad right
you could replace it but it doesn't
matter there might be a case where you
have to replace the link the route when
and when in fact the cost increases
there might be a case where you hear a
you you have a current cost to the
destination and some current route to
the destination and you hear an
advertisement and you take that
advertisement and you add the link cost
and you find a bigger number and you
might sometimes have to replace it yes
right it could be that what's going on
here is that the cost to the destination
you know a link I might I previously
told you that my cost to the destination
is 17 and now I've changed my mind I
tell you that it's actually 19 and I
could change my mind for a variety of
reasons usually having to do with
failure so I guess this is a little bit
of a cheating question because I told
you there's no failures but it could be
that perhaps you know the cost of a link
changed because it became more expensive
or something like that and that's the
only subtle case you have to worry about
where a cost of only the advertisement
could could increase and if that cost
increases along your current route like
you think that the route to the
destination is 17 the cost is 17 but in
fact it turns out to be you know 24
that's the time when you have to change
your entry in the routing table you have
to change the cost associated with it
but otherwise it's basically that's the
algorithm and it's summarized over in
this in the stable I in this chart here
and I've gone through pretty much all of
it does anyone have any questions
no questions
how long does it take before every node
in the network actually before I get to
that the reason it's called a vector
protocol is I showed you a picture for
one destination but in fact each switch
or each node does it for all
destinations so the general form of a
distance vector advertisement looks like
this it has a destination destination 1
: cost one destination to Poland cost to
destination 3 : cost 3 and so forth for
all the destinations to which you have a
cost and initially when you start you
don't know about all of any of the other
nodes if you have a route to some
destination in general then there's some
cost associated with it if you know
about a destination but have no route to
it
the cost is infinity it'll turn out next
week will find that the value of
infinity in this network has to be
pretty small but that's because the
sarvam is not the world's best algorithm
for big networks and I'll explain why
infinity has to be a small number but
theoretically we can assume it's
infinite
the reason it's called a vector protocol
is because the advertisements are a
vector of this destination cost tuples
and so you send these tuples around and
this is a vector of these tuples and
hence this is called a vector protocol
it really should be called cost vector
protocol but initially they ran this
thing where all of the links had cost of
one where and therefore they were
minimizing distance and the name stuck
but if we wanted to be perfectly precise
we would say cost vector but then no one
else in the world would understand what
you meant so we say distance vector okay
any questions all right how long does it
take before every node in the network
for some destination how long does it
has a route to that destination where by
how long I mean how many advertisement
cycles do you have to go through how
many how many of these advertisements
like initially let's say that the way
our world is going to work is initially
every node advertises its own
advertisement to itself then at the next
time step every node advertises their
arts that it knows about and then it
does that periodically so let's say that
every T seconds a node sends out an
advertisement where an advertisement
basically contains this tuple of this
the spec vector of tuples for all of the
destination it knows about right so let
me explain this protocol again and then
I'll ask you the question the protocol
is very simple every T seconds
what what the nodes doing is looking at
two columns in the thriving table it's
looking at the destination column and
the cost column and it's just taking
that information out and it sends out an
advertisement the distance okay every T
seconds how long does it take now let's
focus on one destination D some
destination D in the network and you
have some network how long does it take
before every node has some route to the
destination yes up to the number of
edges in my network all right so let's
say you have a network that looks like
this
how long does it take before every node
has a route to destination be there for
well I'm asking for an answer that holds
for all networks not for sure in the
worst case it could well yes in the
absolute worst case it is true that
it'll always take time smaller than the
number of edges in the network but you
can come up with a much better bound so
let's try to come up yes sir longest
length chain so that's not completely to
the longest what kind of longest length
because you could have a really so
another counter example let's say that I
have this network the longest length
chain is 1 2 3 4 5 6 but yet you guys
just told me that in one shot you get
the answer so you have to clarify what
you meant a little bit you're almost
right
I said find a path or find a route not
the best route how long does it take to
find a route and network you said this
almost the longest path but it's not
quite the longest path it's the longest
something bad yes
the longest shortest path that is the
longest path with the minimum number of
the longest path when you compute the
longest overall paths with a minimum
number of hops between one place to
another that's also called the diameter
of the network okay yes yes okay all
right now that's the time it takes a
multiply by T and I might be off by one
you know it's one minus that minus one
actually it's not it is the number of
hops along the longest shortest path now
how long does it take to find the
minimum cost path - there - to some
destination D at all of the nodes
what
three times no that's that's true that
you can find it within that oh that's
too long so I'm gonna come back to this
question it's probably answered in my in
one of the chilla too in chapter 18 I
think but we'll come back to that next
time it'll become a little bit clearer
but you should think about it there's a
nice succinct answer to this question
and generally speaking in every quiz
there's some variant of this question so
you know it's not explicit but there's
some story that looked wise if yes you
have an answer
oh you do okay I'll come back to that
question next time but yes yeah I can go
over that so let's say you have here
you look at this destination beam and
you look at from every node what's the
path with the smallest number of hops
number of hops not cost path with the
smallest number of hops to get to that
destination right so this guy it's one
two three four this guy it's one two
three etc whatever that biggest number
is multiplied by T is the answer that's
how long it takes before every node here
some pack but it's not quite the right
answer for the best path because as you
saw in this example here it took us one
step before n to God a proud to the
destination but it took us two time
steps before it got its best route to
the destination and the reason was that
has something to do with the length of
the minimum cost path right because in
this case the length of the minimum cost
path is two plus six eight it took two
hops which is different from the length
of some shortest hop path which was one
half so if I look at this picture and to
here's about some route to the
destination in the first advertisement
but then to find its best route to the
destination requires us to actually wait
around until we find this two plus six
path which took two hops so it's a
little longer but it's not like
enormously long it's just a little bit
longer and the answer of course depends
on in the worst case it could be quite
long but it depends on the number of
hops along the minimum cost path and if
you minimize that quantity you find the
answer to the question how long does it
take before every node finds the minimum
cost path to the destination
okay is that clear any questions about
distance-vector crystal fear okay we'll
see when the lab comes around
it is crystal everybody really really
does well in the slide in these labs
it's a lot of fun hacking the stuff up
so your Olympic medals and you'll
actually look at all sorts of failures
and it'll just be sometimes miraculous
that it actually works even when you
didn't consider some failure cases okay
now I'm going to talk about link state
routing and this is the routing protocol
that you guys were sort of attempting to
implement attempting to come up with
this is a radically different approach
from the vector protocols in a vector
protocol everybody advertises for each
destination a vector of tuples where
it's the destination and the cost in a
link state protocol we don't do that the
link state protocol
does not compute in a distributed way in
a link state protocol every node just
says I am node 17 and I am connected to
1645 and 44 and the cost of my link to
16 is 7 the cost of my link to 45 is
something and the cost of my link to
this other neigh​bor that I have is
something else
so every node advertises what I've shown
up on the slide every node advertises a
neigh​bor it's immediate neigh​bor and the
link cost to that neigh​bor okay in
addition in each of these link state
advertisements there is a sequence
number the sequence number starts at
some initial value like say zero and
every time one of these link-state
advertisements is sent and that's done
periodically as well every T seconds
every time you send a link state
advertisement you increment the sequence
number by one
now here's the key step the key step
here is that when a node receives if I
receive a link state advertisement from
you I just send that to my neigh​bors and
then my neigh​bors will send it to their
neigh​bors and so on so it's a very this
nice flooding protocol every node sends
out its link state advertisement and
every neigh​bor that receives it
processes that and then turns around and
ships it to their neigh​bors and they do
the same thing to their neigh​bors and so
forth now when this flooding process
completes and every node is originating
its own link-state advertisements so
you're telling them you know your
neigh​bors who you're connected to she's
telling her neigh​bors who she's
connected to and we all do that and
we're all doing this in parallel it's
all happening at the same time and all
our neigh​bors are rebroadcasting this
and eventually every nodes going to get
one or more copies of every link state
advertisement which means that every
node can now construct an entire map of
the network every node can construct
this entire graph and once they
construct that graph every node can
implement some shortest path routing
protocol to compute the paths over that
graph this is very different from the
previous protocol in vector routing
protocols the nodes actually have no
idea what the topology of the network is
all they know is and they trust what the
neigh​bors tell them here every node has
complete knowledge under the basic model
every node has complete knowledge of the
overall network topology so let me show
this by example
become completely clear so let's imagine
that this is what the network looks like
and you start I'm going to show you a
picture of no death no deaf originates
its initial link-state advertisements a
day Iseman it increments the sequence
number by one and it says I am connected
to G with no G with a cost of eight and
the node C with a cost of two and it
spits it out to its neigh​bors each of
those neigh​bors turns around and does
the same thing you rebroadcast a
link-state advertisement along the links
that you're connected to and they
rebroadcast it and so forth and
eventually be get said and he broadcasts
it too though it was completely useless
to do so well not completely packets are
lost it's pretty useful anyway when this
flooding completes which takes you know
some number of steps every node now has
at least one if no packets are lost
every node has a bunch of copies of this
link state advertisement if packets can
get lost as long as the loss rates are
not you know enormous every node might
have one copy of a link state
advertisement and now every node
originates its own link-state
advertisements and therefore they end up
with a map of the network by the way why
do we have the sequence number in the
link state advertisement
yes
yes that is one of the two reasons why
you have it that's actually the second
reason the main reason you have and
that's a valid reason but the main
reason you have it is that if si gets a
link-state advertisement originating
from F with sequence number 17 and then
eventually C is also going to get D
rebroadcasting that link-state
advertisements ends it this way but F
also sends it this way and that goes up
here and that comes down here and then D
rebroadcast said C needs a way of
telling whether this link-state
advertisement is new or old right and
the way it tells if it's new or old is
it considers the link-state
advertisements bigger than the last
sequence number it received from that
origin so now every note has a map of
the network and now we run this
integration step where we actually take
this map of the network and we find
shortest paths to the network I need a
show of hands how many people know how
Dijkstra's algorithm works from how many
people don't know how it works all right
what I'm going to do is it's described
very well in the notes we've talked
about in recitation tomorrow but I'm
going to show it by example and then
we'll come back to this again on Monday
but I'm going to tell you this now
because you kind of need it for the lab
and it is just that very well in the
readings and we'll do it in recitation
as well so here's how it works let's
imagine we want to find paths from a to
all of the other nodes in the network
now initially a doesn't know paths to
anyone except for itself but what a nose
is this map of the network and what is
trying to do is to find routes to all
the other destinations the way does that
is it keeps building up in non
decreasing order of the cost of the
minimum cost path to the destination it
starts building up information about the
routes to the different destination so
initially it looks
the stable and it says it's connected to
C and it's connected to B with a cost of
six so what it does is it says all right
among all of the people out here I'm
going to pull in the person with the
minimum that minimum cost path and it
might pick in this case it might just
pick the node C because between C and B
it doesn't matter which one it takes now
the cost to all of the other guys is
considered to be infinity so it has
costs of six and six so it pulls in one
of them by without loss of generality it
just picks one of them and now it has
cost to both of them and it says that
the route from a itself at a the route
to see is this link what it then does is
it goes and looks at all of the
neigh​bors connected to a and C and in
fact it only has to look at the New
Nordic pulled in and it has to adjust
the cost of the minimum cost path to the
destination that's connected to that in
this case it adjusts from infinity it
brings down the cost to be to 13 because
it knows that it can get to C is 6 6
plus 7 is 13 similarly it does that for
e at 10 and then it does that to F at 8
so now it has costs of 66.6 is already
in 6 13 10 and 8 and infinity so now it
has to decide what node to pull in next
and it pulls in the node with the
minimum cost among the costs that you
have so far and that's this node over
here so it pulls that in if my wireless
works there we go and then once it pulls
that in it adjusts the route to that to
be the green link and then it goes ahead
and looks at the neigh​bors of B and it
adjusts the shortest path cost in this
case that 13 now becomes 11 because 6
plus 5 going through B is shorter than 6
plus 7 going through C
and now it repeats it pulls down the
minimum the minimum of this case is 8 it
pulls in F makes that be the route to F
now the route to F is not that link the
route to F is in fact this link at the
routing table but it knows that because
it knows that F is connected to C and
therefore the route to F is equal to the
route to the parent which is C's
therefore in the throttle table entry it
makes the route to FB that link which is
exactly the link to C so that's the
subtlety you have to keep in mind when
you implement this stuff in the lab it
goes ahead and adjust that to 16 it now
pulls the minimum which will be 10 and
then adjusts the cost of the guys
connected to it so D becomes D changes
to 10 and then it now goes ahead and
pulls the minimum in in this case it's
12 its D with a cost of 10 that's the
link to use and that link there for the
route to D is the same as there are two
e there are two E's the same as there
are two C which is that link and now you
finally conclude the algorithm by
getting that last node here so I'm going
to stop here that was Dijkstra's
algorithm and the two routing protocols
we will pick it up in recitation